you
we saw yesterday as fear just stay to do
that proof about what kinds of surfaces
you have in the universe the
classification of all surfaces due to a
19th century mathematician called the
Mobius and according to them we had two
types two sequences of surfaces the
sequence that we call Sigma those were
the orientable ones and sequence that we
called new or any non-orientable ones
Sigma's were connected sons of poor I
got Sinatra handles new were a little
weird you had a sphere you took out a
number holes and you put the lids back
in but not ordinary bits rather moves
that's something I was supposed to go
they keep texting alarms but I mean if
the alarm is going all the time then
when the alarm sounds people who think
that it's being tested oh okay so that's
the classification however didn't you
want that like this suppose that you
have both handles and movie strips some
surfaces like this yeah look like a
mixture of Sigma onion
question then where does it see into the
first page in the classification of
substance which was stated in the 0:19
yeah it should be just a bunch of
handles or just a bunch of movie strips
but there might be a mixture so how do
you do this now we shall discuss a very
beautiful technique wonderful technique
called handle sliding in order to
discuss the technique we need a lemon
that's number 21 here's the map let's
look at consider the simplest kind of
mixture that is when you have one handle
and one will be straight and we would
want to know what this is it turns out
that this is homeomorphic to just three
movie streets and what do we call a
surface like this hey from yesterday and
a one and A three no.3 that's right
anything
so if you have a sphere make a hole and
put in a motor strip and attach a handle
that surface is homeomorphic so to
politically the same as a sphere with
three moving strips okay it turns out
and that's the key dep let's prove this
lemma and then we'll proceed the handle
side the way we do it is the following
let's imagine that this handle can be
moved on the surface and we can slide it
all over the service here's the picture
we grab a handle
and then we try to move it t see the
handle and slide it onto the move
okay what's going to happen well first
imagine that there is no movie strip
here and then a go can you see and then
I slide it and slide it and then you
come back to the where you started the
same time there's no mystery about that
but when you go over movie strip
something magical happens this is one of
those magic zones where lots and lots of
strange things happen and when you come
out to you are no longer the same here's
how it goes when you go in this movie
strip which we are simply noting by this
cross picture is in fact Maria's picture
which a more familiar with looks like
this
and that's what happens when this handle
arrives on the list this is the handle
sticking out from the outside and that's
now attached to the part of the surface
which is move east let's slide this
handle all the way around movie strip
once what's going up
well next picture is going to be this
the handle comes here it's sliding a
study
and then you keep starting but you see -
slide is handled you see Matt appoints
the handle comes over on this side yeah
so whereas I was on this side the handle
comes over on the other side I'm coming
out from the outside and then sorry I
come around this this way so the next
instant we get the attachment to the
handle which will be over here
okay and then I keep going I just keep
sliding the handle and amazingly when
you come out of the movie stood the
fourth fixture
the handle is now attached to the other
side of the movie strip I hope you can
see when I arrive where as I started
from one side it emerges on the other
side because I went to run movie strip
once it's like running your finger and
when you go around movie strip being
one-sided whoop you come out on on the
other side so then I go out okay
then I go out of the movie strip be
around the movie strip
what
now come out the result is I'm going to
draw it here instead of having a picture
like that now the handle is attached to
the other side of the surface like this
and this picture should seem familiar to
all of you from yesterday look at the
right half of the picture that is one of
the pictures of the climate all which we
discussed at the end of yesterday this
side there is still that same a little
strip which is sitting yep so this half
is a climate and you remember what the
climate all is in terms of movie strips
we can draw this picture of the kind of
which by theorem oops sorry
which example was this we discussed by
example 20 is a pair of movie strips so
the conclusion is that this picture can
be replaced by this picture so the whole
thing was three movie streets and very
curious kind of proof we have never seen
a proof like this but it's completely
rigorous and indeed very useful later on
to show you the first use now we have
the possibility of doing arithmetic that
is when you learn arithmetic you have a
table multiplication you know 3 times 4
is 12 and 5 times 7 is 42 35 and so on
so well let's have a table of connected
sound exactly table bodies
jakers well what can you add well oh you
can add ever according to the
classification theorem is either Sigma
or new so you might cross that adding
Sigma G to say Sigma G Prime
that's analogy for example Sigma 2 2
Sigma 3 or maybe you g 2 Sigma G Prime
for example new for 2 Sigma 5 or
something like that only they can i've
new to you and so so we have to
understand what the results are for all
of these some of these entries are very
easy what do you think we get if I see
man if I take the connected sum of Sigma
J and Sigma G prefer of course you just
have G handles G prime handles together
you get on the sum of the handles that's
all how about mu G mu G prime well
similarly as Jimin says it's just this
the only tricky parts are those two
entries yeah but that we can do by the
and using dilemma okay so this is the
collectible coin exam it turns out that
this entry in fact I can try to do the
calculation in my head if I braid G + 2
G prime it turns out so you are not
adding G and you find that you double
this Sigma B problem and similarly here
it see I'm symmetric so G prime plus 2 G
okay so you almost always get use all
three entries out of four years news you
get none on orient a bit okay here is
the proof for those of diagonal entries
the only
non-trivial entries that we diagnose so
we shall focus our effort contacts
so let's try to see what happens if I
add for example Sigma G and new G Prime
yeah I kind of push excuse me
so you want to take the connect son of a
sub such as like this which is Sigma G
and then just buy some with a surface
like this which is mu G Prime so they
are supposed to be G of those handles
and G prime of those movie strips so how
do you cut it down I'm going to continue
that calculation over here
so if you can go from there to here that
last pitch a supposed to be chromium
over to the next picture so let's put
that picture in the mall suggests before
will handle you have those handles G of
them and then those movie slips
gee family so that's the service that we
have to understand which surface is this
well exactly the same argument as before
but now we have lots of handles let's
grab this hand go for example and slide
it and go around movie strip once and
come out okay each time I do that I
convert this handle from outside outside
to this strange crime type and oh that
goes from outside to inside exactly by
this process so after you slide this
yeah in the course of which you are not
changing your homeomorphism time it's
always the same surface I'm just
deforming it continuously without
tearing anything you end up with this
picture
okay now how many of these handles are
there geode how many of those movie
strips are there G primal and let us
look at the composition of the picture
just like so so each of these bits is a
climate but the climate all according to
the fundamental lemma that we have I'm
sorry example 20 that we discussed and
upon a lemma splits into two movie
suggests so I can replace each of these
strange clients handle by two movie
strips and the result is going to be
where you have already understood that's
going to be those movies tricks just
survive that being touched and each of
these will give rise to two movie
scripts so how many pairs of these other
well they were G of them so that to G
and I'm here there G prime of them hence
that result okay so you see how
wonderful this strange but useful
notation is I mean this is supposed to
be this complicated operation taking out
the whole and then gluing back a movie
strip by identifying the boundary circle
movie strip the boundaries of this whole
it's a very complicated and rather
mysterious operation which as I keep
saying you cannot do
in a three-dimensional space but you can
nonetheless hydrate and have a complete
misako understanding or what happens if
you add and put together various
surfaces you start seeing thanks to
geometry and topology things that you
cannot physically and in ordinary life
see your vision is now being expanded to
better things
okay so that's what it is okay now a
little remark before we close this
section remark 23 we decided in that
table option connected some as well as
in the classification scheme to try to
UM
you know reduce everything to just Sigma
or n in other words express everything
in terms of handles everything in terms
of movie strips and we didn't want to
have a mixture of those these two
however another approach is possible
maybe you see here initially you had
only G prime will be strips but I can't
we have so many movie strips maybe you
don't like movie strips yeah in that
case let's minimize number Buddha strips
well here's an idea if you have two
movie strips you can combine them to
make a kind of okay and if you have a
third movie strip I can slide that
climate around and make it in the handle
in a rating reverse operation what we
have done so
we may wish to minimize in each
representational surface the number of
movie strips in which case what you get
is as follows Sigma G of course looks
like G handles attached to a sphere so
that's the picture of Sigma G but what
about this and picture and it turns out
that if you have any G where G is odd
you have a fixture like this a lot of
handles together with just one movies
strip
that's an odd why is this because if you
have an odd number movie strip you can
combine them two by two but there will
be one left over each combined pair of
movie strips will become a climate or
climate all which you pull slide it
around the remaining movie strip will
become a handle and so you get all those
handles plus the remaining movie strip
if you have an N even then you have this
standard form for minimizing the movie
strip
just to publish tips and any number of
handles again you combine all the and
movie sticks pair pair wise but you have
to leave to at the end
why because you see if I combine these
to make a climb at all then there's no
more that magic zone left over which
slide decline both oh I'm a keeping the
handle I have to leave this patch of
magic land where you'll go in and come
back on the other side that's a movie
strip so in order to keep this reversal
process I have to leave at least one
movie strip but that makes me obliged to
leave too at the same time so you get
this standard form when you have an old
the standard form is number of handles
plus one movie strip and even number of
handles plus two new tricks that is a
digression you don't have to worry too
much about
imagine
why do I leave - okay suppose that is
you say that - movie strips left you say
ah I know what to do then I have two
movies tricks I can combine them to make
a climate also climate Oh which starts
outside and somehow connects back inside
and then you want to say oh I don't like
this time but I want to turn it into a
handle yeah
so what I mean is start from here and go
back there but you see another goal from
inside outside outside inside you need
one movie strip okay so at this stage if
you combine you can leave it in the form
of bunch of handles plus one time that's
okay too but I'm just saying if you want
to represent all the surfaces in terms
of handles and movie strips so in
particular no climb at all and you want
to minimize number of movies strips this
is the standard form you might want to
represent things in terms of climate
balls and handles and so that's another
random matter okay good any questions
about this is whole story you have now
covered the whole of topology with some
sort of fan which also admitted but
essentially the all the main ideas of
the topology of dimension - you know all
the surfaces that can exist in the
universe or the compaction without
boundary surfaces and you know how to
manipulate them you know how to cut them
paste them and so on in fact where you
have learnt the serial surgery by the
way the surgery theory that which I
present a few dimensional two
dimensional version exists in higher
dimensions as well it's much more
interesting a little more difficult and
there's a whole sort of
subject which was built in the 1960s and
70s that classified what was very
powerful in classifying manacles by
cutting and pasting sliding handles and
things like this this is the lowest
dimensional example which is already
interesting there was an instant where
in a bookstore in New York there was a
book on mathematical surgery theory of
surgery
sorry surgery on simply connected
manifolds and a student went to buy this
and couldn't find it in a mathematical
section and finally found it in the
medical section
good okay we shall now start the second
chapter of this course entitled isotopy
you might wonder what I study is in a
more familiar turn it is how could be
for various subjects the theory of
deformations we have used the idea of
deformation already in the beginning
when we discussed solving problems by
deformation in terms of examples and we
also had some sort of deformation
arguments so first sliding handles and
so on but now we shall discuss
systematically how to deform various
objects in all directions and in
particular the relationship between
deformation and dimensions various
spaces we will now learn the object of
this section how to move stop manholes
inside an ambient manual
remember that manifold is just a
geometric figure or some dimension so if
you have some sort of spatial manifold
and we have some geometric figure inside
that's called so manifold how do you
move it around the manifold and you'll
see with various examples what we mean
but to begin let's discuss really the
simple but essential case
on the plane r2
if you have two lines how are they
positioned with respect to each other do
they cross or do they not cross two
lines on the plane what do you think
where they cross and you know somebody
very alert like a chimney Irish will say
that all but their case is when they
don't cross when they are para but
usually they cause this is a stable
picture and only exception it will add a
package so two lines we say generically
this means usually stabili you know
accepting really unlucky circumstances
you guys directly intersect in a point
two lines have dimension one and damage
from luggage the point has dimension
zero you see that one plus one yeah
minus two is zero it turns out not to be
an accident
there are cases lines that do not ex do
not intersect as you are going to
complain is the entire case but these
cases are degenerate
I'm not defining what generic
conditioners are I'm hoping that you
understand you have an intuition about
what these things are from the examples
vision so there if you like exceptional
and like unstable in the sense that if
you perturb it a little bit they
immediately become impaired oh yeah and
unlucky probability zero and so on so so
generally they intersect in a point
let's go to our face in r3 a lie and the
plane
what do they look like and the line like
this intersect in a single point okay
there might be cases when the arrow but
that's going to be quite a much so an
onion like line has dimension one I'm
playing a dimension to intersect in a
point which has dimension zero
okay you know that one plus two minus
three is zero
how about then a plane and the plane
what do you think if you have to two
dimensional planes inside are three how
do they intercept it can intersect along
the line that line is a one-dimensional
intersection so in general if you have a
K dimensional subspace and the elder
missional subspace in an M dimensional
space how do we intersect what's the
intersection damage
something like that okay we all have our
conjectures I'm very happy to hear you
say so okay so but in this case two
things generically intersect in life
yeah we will understand that and picture
that I shall draw is this kind of
picture
so that's that's neat
okay
good and of course here again their
degeneration you can have a playing on
the line which are parallel to each
other or maybe playing and the line
which is inside a plane or two planes
that are parallel to each other or two
planes that coincide just exactly on top
of each other and so in that case of
course the intersection is empty
intersection is just a line intersection
is empty here and intersection is the
plane itself so in all those cases you
don't have a conclusion that we have but
those are degenerate cases that's then
summarized but our conjecture see on one
why are we back to one because it's a
new chapter let K and L inside M
the sub manifolds inside the manifold M
or if you like subspaces inside space m
and so you give them the meaning you
like and let us call this strange number
dimension of k plus dimension well minus
the dimension of M this number which can
be positive negative or zero we shall
hold the overflow and we'll see in a
moment why it's called over this term is
not standard I invented this term and we
shall use it in the same scores well why
do is call it other Pro okay it's why
you see the ambient dimension dimension
the Box in which the space in which we
are trying to fit K and L has dimension
M it has a certain dimension now it's
very tricky that if you try to put a
very large K and very large L they will
not be able to fit separately yeah they
all have to start crossing because there
isn't enough space in the ambient space
to fit those to accommodate those sub
manifolds so how much overflow is there
that's exactly this so you try to put K
and L together and this is as much room
as there is and if you have too much
again in a too little space then you
over so if you have plenty of onion
space and yellow/green very much then
you have plenty of space that overflow
is still negative in a most negative
overflow that means there is no possible
okay so this is how much
and overflow you create how much
dimension overflows when we try to fit
force fitting back
okay and L into em that's the intuitive
interpretation that's why it's called
overflow it might be a little strange to
think of a negative overflow but when
it's negative that means they still you
have still space with that now ah okay I
shall have to go there I'm sorry I like
to state a theorem on the same
blackboard but sometimes I miss time
myself